Guide to the Ray Millholland Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ray Millholland papers
1936-1946
MS 1204
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes)
Typescripts of two books, a screenplay, and several short stories with related correspondence and memorabilia. Splinter Fleet, published in 1936, concerns his experiences in World War I in the U.S. Navy. Pay Day, published in 1946, is about labor and management in America.
Millholland, Ray
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ray Millholland, 1939-1946.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Ray Milholland Papers contain drafts of five writings by Millholland, accompanied by related correspondence and printed matter. The earliest material consists of a draft of Millholland's book, The Splinter Fleet, about his experience during World War I in the U.S. Navy, and newspaper clippings and reviews of the book. This material is followed by a draft of the short story "Diesel Cumshaw" and correspondence on its publication in the Saturday Evening Post. The next short story, "Island Doctor," is represented by a draft, a printed copy, and a screenplay adaptation, as well as by an "Author's Note" by Millholland and correspondence from readers expressing criticism and favorable comments.
The largest amount of material is related to Millholland's article "Biggest War Baby," a discussion of the machine tool industry. Included are a draft of the article, correspondence between Millholland and his publisher which determined the article's eventual point of view, letters from readers, and related printed material. Further correspondence and reviews and newspaper clippings are contained in a scrapbook devoted to the article.
The final item in the collection is a draft of Pay Day, Millholland's book on labor and management in America. The entire collection was given to Yale University by Ray Millholland between 1940 and 1946.
Business; Working class; World War, 1914-1918; Authors; Labor movement; Labor; Millholland, Ray
- Inventory
  - The Splinter Fleet
    - Ms and typescript draft, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1936-37 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Diesel Cumshaw"
    - Typescript draft, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Island Doctor"
    - Printed copy, ms draft, screenplay adaptation, "Author's Note", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Biggest War Baby"
    - Typescript draft, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence and printed matter, 1939-40 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      General
      See also: Inventory Box 2
  - Pay Day: typescript draft, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, re: "Biggest War Baby" (Box 2)